A Guide to the Papers of the Twin Oaks Community,
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Twin Oaks Community
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
9840 -s, -t, -u, -v, -w
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Permission of the Twin Oaks Communities Board is required for access.
Acquisition Information
This collection was received in five groups as a deposit from the Twin Oaks Community, Route 4, Box 169 Louisa, Virginia 23093. The first part, 9840-s, was received on August 11, 2000. The second part, 9840-t, was received on May 18, 2001. The third part, 9840-u, was received on August 16, 2001. The fourth part of the collection, 9840-v, was received on December 3, 2001. The fifth part, 9840-w, was received on December 17, 2004.
Biographical/Historical Information
Twin Oaks is a collective settlement established in 1967 in Louisa County, Virginia and inspired by B.F. Skinner's Walden Two. The leadership of the Twin Oaks Community is a group of two or three members who serve on a board called Community Planners, the terms of which rotate after a designated period of time. Members write opinion and idea papers and post ideas on a community bulletin board in order to contribute their input regarding all of the decisions made by the community planners.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of 11,073 items, 48 Hollinger boxes, and 240 linear feet and includes information about the councils, controversial issues, correspondence, and culture of the Twin Oaks Community in Louisa, Virginia from 1970-1989 and 1997.
Most of the papers are organized by councils composed of Twin Oaks members, including the Agriculture Council, Child Council, Construction and Utilities Council, Culinary Council, Domestic Council, Health Council, HEW Council, Income Council, Office Council, Outreach Council, Planning Council, Support Council, and Transportation and Maintenance Council. These papers consist of meeting minutes, reports, planning notes, surveys, trade-off games, and budget priorities.
Areas of special interest include photographs of cows that live at Twin Oaks (under the Agriculture Council), opinion and idea papers that are written by members, planner's meeting minutes that reveal the inner workings of Twin Oaks and individual personalities and relationships of the members and planners. (Opinion and idea papers and planner's meeting minutes can be found under each council depending on the subject.)
There is also information under the Income Council that describes the products and work that is marketed at Twin Oaks such as hammocks, tofu, indexing for the government and designs for numeric keyboards.
The community has discussions regarding ratios of men to women in the community and a desire to create a more sincerely balanced society of men and women. The discussion is included under the Outreach Council.
Another interesting item in the collection is the adoption of a South American refugee family into the Twin Oaks Community. More information about this can be found under the Support Council.
Under the Planning Council and Legal Issues there is information about a member of Twin Oaks who is accused of armed robbery, grand larceny, felonious assault and use of a fire arm against a Charlottesville Jeweler, George Moody in 1980. Moody was later murdered in 1996 during an unrelated robbery. The papers include discussions encouraging members to give information to the police, debates about how to handle the remaining possessions of the member since he was expelled and legal advice regarding compensation for the items stolen.
Also under the Planning Council and Legal Issues is a plan of prevention against the possible return of an ex-member who is feared to be violent.
Other areas of interest are the controversial issues that arise in the community such as the issue of nudity around visitors and its impact on teenagers; noise; smoking; vandalism and other infractions. One notable incident is when the planners allow a senior citizen the special privilege of watching television when it is not allowed for other members and members are found in her room watching a program together and refuse to stop. Another issue for members is that they have to earn quotas in hammock making while their other skills are being ignored. While members and planners struggle to work out these controversies, the papers show their strong desire to be a community that loves and respects its members.
Arrangement
This collection is divided into four series, the first of which is Councils and is arranged alphabetically by each council name. The second series consists of correspondence, including letters between members and visitors or members who are away, and is arranged alphabetically by topic. The third series concerns controversial issues that have developed at Twin Oaks and is also arranged alphabetically by topic. The fourth series is Culture, arranged alphabetically by topic, and includes artwork, books, children's activities, education, and food menus, as well as publications about Twin Oaks, spirituality, feminism, and values. There are opinion and idea papers for almost every topic that is pertinent to Twin Oaks, and they are included throughout this collection under the various subcategories organized by council.
Contents List
- Series 1: Councils
  - A. Agriculture Council
    - Agriculture Council, Dairy Farm, 1981-1987, 17 items. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Budget proposal and dairy farm planning worksheet; updates on the health of the cows; 2 photographs of the cows; opinion and idea papers about cows.
    - Agriculture Council, Farming, 1978; n.d., 8 items. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Farm reports and proposals; opinion and idea papers about the need for long term planning for farming and the benefits and costs of farming.
    - Agriculture Council, Farming, 1980; 1988-1989, 14 items. (Box-folder 1:3)
      Planners report on establishing a budget and priorities for farming; plan-writing worksheet; survey plat; letters to planners requesting funds and/or equipment; request for a three day permaculture gathering; request to rent or hire hay balers; request to use the central field for grazing; Twin Oaks farm newsletters titled Deep Furrows.
    - Agriculture Council, Farming Costs and Opinion and Idea Papers, 1978-1983, 32 items. (Box-folder 1:4)
      Yearly cash flow analyses; list of non-income farm fixed assets; figures on possible selling of machinery and expenses; opinion and idea papers on farming.
    - Agriculture Council, Food & Land Survey, n.d., 2 items. (Box-folder 1:5)
      Survey about self-sufficiency in food and the effects of population on agricultural land needs.
    - Agriculture Council, Garden and Orchard [Vegetables and fruits], 1982-1989, 20 items. (Box-folder 1:6)
      Reports; requests for piping and irrigation in the fall; opinion and idea papers about organic farming and other issues; garden and orchard plan-writing worksheets.
    - Agriculture Council, Garden Compost, 1981-1987, 6 items. (Box-folder 1:7)
      Notes on controlling houseflies; proposals for compost pit; research paper on compost; meeting notes.
    - Agriculture Council, Herb Garden, 1988, 2 items. (Box-folder 1:8)
      Progress report; list of herbs and sketched layout.
    - Agriculture Council, Labor and Other Projects, 1984; 1988-1989, 3 items. (Box-folder 1:9)
      Letter to planners requesting a new gate for the field; information about bees; plan-writing worksheet; proposal to grow mushrooms.
    - Agriculture Council, Pigs, 1982-1985, 7 items. (Box-folder 1:10)
      Reports on the health and progress of pigs; warning notes about feeding pigs; a schedule for the pig program.
    - Agriculture Council, Poultry and Geese, 1979-1980; 1989, 7 items. (Box-folder 1:11)
      Proposal and notes about raising gosling at Twin Oaks; recommendation about moving the location of the chickens or discontinue raising them.
    - Agriculture Council, Yard, 1983-1989, 17 items. (Box-folder 1:12)
      Yard plan-writing worksheet; reports and proposals on flower, tree, shrub plantings and sheds; opinion and idea paper about the purchase and placement of a Japanese Peace Pole; opinion and idea paper and policies regarding keeping the yard clean.
  - B. Child Council
    - Child Council. Child Board, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 1:13)
      Meeting notes.
    - Child Council. Child Board, 1980-1983, 105 items. (Box-folder 1:14)
      Board meeting notes; meeting agendas; letter from Twin Oaks to people interested in their child program.
    - Child Council. Child Board, 1986-1988, 39 items. (Box-folder 1:15)
      Meeting notes; budget sheet; report on 6 month audit for child council; notes on child transportation budget; 1988-1989 budget worksheet; opinion and idea paper on child program by ex-member Paul Zohav.
    - Child Council. Child Board, 1989-1993, n.d., 15 items. (Box-folder 1:16)
      Results of the primary poll; child behavior norms and rules; reorganization policy; adult/child sexual activity policy.
    - Child Council. Child Budget, 1983-1992; n.d., 48 items. (Box-folder 1:17)
      Plan-writing worksheet for child council; OTRA request form; budget sheet.
    - Child Council. Complaints About Children, 1984, 1 item. (Box-folder 1:18)
      One letter of complaint involving children.
    - Child Council. Child Housing, 1983-1985, 2 items. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Results and notes from planning child housing poll.
    - Child Council. Meta Child Process, 1988, 15 items. (Box-folder 2:2)
      Process in hiring facilitators; progress reports; questions regarding the child program; meeting notes.
    - Child Council. Meta Meeting Notes, 1978-1981, 27 items. (Box-folder 2:3)
      Meta meeting notes and reports from various Twin Oaks members; OS meeting notes 1981, Feb 4.
    - Child Council. Population and Statistics, 1988, 4 items. (Box-folder 2:4)
      Packet on child labor and budgets; statistic on child population in 1988.
    - Child Council. Programs, 1984-1988, 11 items. (Box-folder 2:5)
  - C. Construction and Utilities Council
    - Construction and Utilities Council. Building Maintenance, 1982-1989, 30 items. (Box-folder 2:6)
      Committee report; necessary building maintenance; plan-writing worksheet; meeting notes; opinion and idea papers on various maintenance projects; plans for the chimney brush room.
    - Construction & Utilities Council. Construction, 1971; 1975; 1978-1989, 27 items. (Box-folder 2:7)
      List of construction workers and their schedules; list of projects; goods and services inventory; expense sheets; meeting notes; updates on maintenance projects such as the greenhouse or sink and shower replacement; requests for drink machine; draft of Energy Self-Sufficiency Loan Proposal; update on construction of Modern Times.
    - Construction and Utilities Council. Equipment Maintenance, 1986-1989, 8 items. (Box-folder 2:8)
      Letters to planner requesting equipment maintenance; plan-writing worksheet; technical manual for organ.
    - Construction and Utilities Council. Forestry, 1982; 1987-1988, 11 items. (Box-folder 2:9)
      Area worksheet/plan-writing worksheet and economic plans.
    - Construction and Utilities Council. Heating and Air-Conditioning, 1980-1989, 27 items. (Box-folder 2:10)
      Heat loss worksheet; proposed layout of boiler room; wood heating; tips for using air-conditioners; opinion and idea papers.
    - Construction and Utilities Council. Paths and Landscaping, 1977; 1986-1989, 5 items. (Box-folder 2:11)
      Reports and proposals.
    - Construction & Utilities Council. Project Aurora, 1986-1987, 22 items. (Box-folder 2:12)
      Opinion and idea papers on the construction and naming of Aurora, the new visitor center; labor chart for construction; list of materials; invoices and blueprints (some oversize).
    - Construction & Utilities Council. Project Llano Remodel, 1986-1988, 4 items. (Box-folder 2:13)
      Notes on remodeling including labor costs.
    - Construction & Utilities Council. Project Morningstar, 1976, 2 items. (Box-folder 2:14)
      Updates on its construction.
    - Construction & Utilities Council. Project Zhankoye, 1984-1986, 31 items. (Box-folder 2:15)
      Notes and discussion about naming Zhankoye, the new Kitchen Dining Complex; budget reports; meeting notes about going over the budget; list of equipment needed for opening; landscaping around Zhankoye.
    - Construction & Utilities Council. Sewer Treatment Plan, 1974; 1987-1988, 10 items. (Box-folder 2:16)
      Revised waterworks regulations; letter from the department of health concerning the waterworks regulations and the operations permit compliance; STP planning worksheet; opinion and idea papers about the river and warnings about what goes into the drains and toilets; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University certificate of wastewater treatment operator for a Twin Oaks member.
    - Construction & Utilities Council. Publication about Soil. Can You Afford Not to Look at Soils? 1971 August, 1 item. (Box-folder 2:17)
      Publication by Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University.
    - Construction & Utilities Council. Publication about Soil. Soils for Homesites, 1971 May, 1 item. (Box-folder 2:18)
      Packet on various issues regarding soil by the extension division at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University.
    - Construction & Utilities Council. Utilities Maintenance, 1974-1991, 17 items. (Box-folder 3:1)
      Reports from the Department of Health show bacteriological contamination in the samples of water that they tested; plan-writing worksheet; purchase approved for a generator; information about the new ventilation system; information regarding the need for new water pipes; opinion and idea papers about the Zhankoye heating system.
    - Construction & Utilities Council. Woodshop, 1983-1989, 11 items. (Box-folder 3:2)
      Opinion and idea papers on cleaning and organizing the woodshop; lumber storage shed needs repair; planning worksheet.
  - D. Culinary Council
    - Culinary Council. Cook, 1982-1989, 20 items. (Box-folder 3:3)
      Notes about needing more chefs and surveys about food; opinion and idea papers on serving lines and second helpings.
    - Culinary Council. Food, 1974-1986, 55 items. (Box-folder 3:4)
      Food budget worksheet; food policies; notes on purchasing coffee and soy products; opinion and idea papers.
    - Culinary Council. Food, 1987-1989; n.d., 38 items. (Box-folder 3:5)
      Food news updates; food budget; introduction to food at Twin Oaks for visitors; news clipping on bread; recipes; information and notes about purchasing food processing equipment from the Ball Jar Corporation; milk processing and production; food processing budget worksheet
    - Culinary Council. Food Management [Food Papers by Rico], 1980-1982, 15 items. (Box-folder 3:6)
      Food updates.
    - Culinary Council. Kitchen and Cleaning, 1986-1987, 15 items. (Box-folder 3:7)
      Zhankoye Gazhette [sic] (newsletters); suggestion notebook 1986.
    - Culinary Council. Kitchen and Cleaning, 1983-1989; n.d., 38 items. (Box-folder 3:8)
      Budget worksheet and policies; opinion and idea papers.
    - Culinary Council. Kitchen and Microwave, 1986-1987, 15 items. (Box-folder 3:9)
      Opinion and idea papers; meeting notes; survey about having microwave at Twin Oaks.
    - Culinary Council. Kitchen Dining Complex Questionnaire, 1976 December, 41 items. (Box-folder 3:10)
  - E. Domestic Council
    - Domestic Council. Activism, n.d., 1 item. (Box-folder 4:1)
      Flyer about nuclear radiation.
    - Domestic Council. Artwork, n.d., 4 items. (Box-folder 4:2)
      Miscellaneous artwork from Twin Oaks members.
    - Domestic Council. Community Clothes, 1982-1990, 17 items. (Box-folder 4:3)
      Updates about location and policies on community clothes; budget plan-writing worksheets.
    - Domestic Council. General, 1985; 1987, 2 items. (Box-folder 4:4)
      Member/Planner apology; opinion and idea paper about different needs and views on the meaning of "home."
    - Domestic Council. House [Cleaning], 1982-1989; n.d., 36 items. (Box-folder 4:5)
      Information on new homemade soap; opinion and idea paper on art gallery; notice-free walls; budget plan-writing worksheet; notes on house cleaning.
    - Domestic Council. Juniper Business Notes, 1975-1976; 1979, 7 items. (Box-folder 4:6)
      Meeting notes and ideas from the Jupiter Business.
    - Domestic Council. Pets, 1981-1985, 29 items. (Box-folder 4:7)
      Policies; opinion and idea papers on various pets; budget planning worksheet.
    - Domestic Council. Pets, 1986-1987, 26 items. (Box-folder 4:8)
      Notes, debates, and discussions pertaining to pets.
    - Domestic Council. Room Assignment, 1977-1990, 30 items. (Box-folder 4:9)
      Room assignments and floor plans.
    - Domestic Council. Small Living Group Survey, n.d., 36 items. (Box-folder 4:10)
      Juniper Branch Planner's poll on small living groups; completed surveys by members and poll results; 1982 small living group handbook suggestions for reorganization of domestic areas; meeting notes; opinion and idea papers.
    - Domestic Council. Trustery [sic], 1978-1988, 13 items. (Box-folder 4:11)
      Information on flip, a program that gives out random items to members by chance; job description of trusterty [sic] managers; notes on flips as loan (trusterty) and flips policy change; opinion and idea papers.
    - Domestic Council. Tupelo Meeting Notes, 1974-1977, 131 items. (Box-folder 4:12)
      Notes composed by various members present at the meetings.
    - Domestic Council. Tupelo Meeting Notes, 1978-1979; n.d., 62 items. (Box-folder 4:13)
  - F. Health Council
    - Health Council. Ageing, 1982-1983; 1996-1997, 4 items. (Box-folder 5:1)
      Final report from the Ageing in Utopia Task Force; notes on labor quota changes for members over fifty years old.
    - Health Council. Budget, 1983-1989, 11 items. (Box-folder 5:2)
      Various economic plans concerning health.
    - Health Council. Chiropractic Needs, 1981-1988, 7 items. (Box-folder 5:3)
      Various announcements pertaining to chiropractic health.
    - Health Council. Dental, 1983; 1988-1989, 5 items. (Box-folder 5:4)
      Dental budget worksheet and other notes on dental issues.
    - Health Council. Health Issues of Members, 1985-1989, 21 items. (Box-folder 5:5)
      Papers documenting the health of particular members.
    - Health Council. Health Team, 1982-1989, 32 items. (Box-folder 5:6)
      Health team policies; new member health information form; new member requirements; first-aid classes; meeting notes; opinion and idea papers.
    - Health Council. HIV and AIDS, 1986-1987, 20 items. (Box-folder 5:7)
      Policies concerning HIV testing; introduction/drawing from a HIV positive guest speaker; opinion and idea papers on sexuality and AIDS; notes on HIV/AIDS issue; e-mail from the AIDS/HIV Service Group about volunteering
    - Health Council. Infestations of Lice, Flies, and Roaches, 1982-1988, 15 items. (Box-folder 5:8)
      Complaints and information relating to insect infestations.
    - Health Council. Insurance from PEACH, 1984-1987, 41 items. (Box-folder 5:9)
      Information and correspondence on PEACH, a new insurance program adopted by Twin Oaks and the FEC.
    - Health Council. Insurance from PEACH, 1988-1989, 11 of items. (Box-folder 5:10)
    - Health Council. Mental Health, 1980-1988, 25 items. (Box-folder 5:11)
      Policies and updates on several members at mental hospitals; information on leave for family emergency; requests for leaves of absence; information on Lifespring, a group that creates educational-experiential self-transformation workshops; information on counseling services.
    - Health Council. Safety and Wellness, 1982-1989, 32 items. (Box-folder 5:12)
      Petition against the Nuclear Regulatory Commission; notes on fire safety; handout on wood smoke; information on radon; warnings about toys distributed by Johnson and Johnson; information on preventive health care.
  - G. HEW Council
    - HEW Council. Adult Education, 1981-1988, 19 items. (Box-folder 5:13)
      Notes and proposals on adult members getting education; budget planning worksheet.
  - H. Income Council
    - Income Council. General, 1978-1983, 4 items. (Box-folder 6:1)
      Sewing business; massage table carrying cases; opinion and idea paper; proposals; notes about businesses at Twin Oaks.
    - Income Council. Hammocks, 1975-1989; n.d., 58 items. (Box-folder 6:2)
      Letters to Twin Oaks from East Wind community; proposal to bring in Short Mountain members to help out with production and other proposals; outline of job description; opinion and idea papers; evaluation and value of hammock production; meeting notes; information notes about Pier 1; letters to Pier 1; policies about attending fairs to sell hammocks; budget sheet; magazine clippings.
    - Income Council. Hammocks. Agreement with East Wind Community, 1977-1988, 12 items. (Box-folder 6:3)
      Questions and answers on agreement; agreement form; opinion and idea papers; 1983 Joint Hammocks Agreement.
    - Income Council. Hammocks. Backpackers, 1976-1986; n.d., 15 items. (Box-folder 6:4)
      Opinion and idea paper about the quality of backpacker hammocks; correspondence of Hudson Bay Outfitters; report.
    - Income Council. Hammocks. Business Management, 1978-1989, 11 items. (Box-folder 6:5)
      Outline of general manager job; resignation letter; meeting notes.
    - Income Council. Hammocks. Business Meeting Notes, 1977-1989, 6 items. (Box-folder 6:6)
    - Income Council. Hammocks. Business Production, 1980-1989, 17 items. (Box-folder 6:7)
      Opinion and idea paper about winter production; maximum and minimum assignable hours.
    - Income Council. Hammocks. Hammocks, Chairs, and Oakweaves, 1979-1990, 15 items. (Box-folder 6:8)
      Instruction to install hammock chairs and oakweaves; opinion and idea paper; license agreement.
    - Income Council. Hammocks. Incentive Program, 1977-1989, 53 items. (Box-folder 6:9)
      Notes on Hammock Incentive Program, or HIP; auction information in the hammock shop; hammock shop events; children's pictures.
    - Income Council. Hammocks. Jig Designs, 1975; n.d., 9 items. (Box-folder 6:10)
      Sketch of hammock jig; notes on measurement for the jig.
    - Income Council. Hammocks. Overquota Projects Program, 1977-1988, 34 items. (Box-folder 6:11)
      Information on OPP, a program that allows members to work in hammock production to benefit certain projects instead of labor credits; meeting notes.
    - Income Council. Hammocks. Overquota Projects Program, 1989-1999, 27 of items. (Box-folder 6:12)
    - Income Council. Hammocks. Product Office, 1981-1990, 6 items. (Box-folder 7:1)
      Proposal to allow beepers; protocol on answering the phone; opinion and idea papers.
    - Income Council. Hammocks. Production, 1986-1989, 15 items. (Box-folder 7:2)
      Documents pertaining to the production of hammocks.
    - Income Council. Hammocks. Reports, 1977-1989, 21 items. (Box-folder 7:3)
      Update from hammock manager; 1978 evaluation of hammock and hammock-related production; opinion and idea paper on hammock business and members involved; quarterly sales report; reports known as "products informant;" income and labor analysis; opinion and idea papers.
    - Income Council. Hammocks. Ropemaking, 1978-1989, 17 items. (Box-folder 7:4)
      Proposals; summary about time at "Warner Swazey;" sketches; survey and meeting notes.
    - Income Council. Hammocks. Sawmill, 1988-1989, 6 items. (Box-folder 7:5)
      Updates on purchasing sawmill; letter from a member.
    - Income Council. Hammocks. Shop, 1981-1989, 21 items. (Box-folder 7:6)